[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net SC radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
[Music]
software for software engineering radio
this is Robert blumen today I am joined
by Luis Rodriguez Luis is the CTO of
zeni where he focuses on supply chain
security prior to agen he held
management positions and consultant
roles at agento and other software
companies Lis welcome to software
engineering radio hi and I appreciate
the opportunity to talk in this uh postc
would you like to say anything about
your background that I didn't mention I
have worked mainly in the application
security uh space for some 15 20 years
more or less mainly on the Bor side I
was uh interested in application
security and software Security in
general and I worked in later projects
in uh the static analysis for
vulnerabilities for application security
vulnerabilities also in the sca space
detecting vulnerabilities on
dependencies on third party dependenc I
felt a bit guilty on producing a lot of
a lot of noise a lot of
vulnerabilities and in fact the new
project which is J which I started as a
co-founder intending to correct that
problem to give a better approach to
managing the vulnerabilities and also
the malware because uh not only the
passive security problems but also the
active ones the issues that third
parties Bad actors are injecting in in
the supply chain this is a which we we
are focus on that right now supply chain
security has been in the news a lot we
have covered it on software engineering
radio a few times episode 535 on supply
chain attacks 541 on securing open
source Supply chains and 606 on
thirdparty supply chain risks today we
will be talking about a celebrated or
maybe I should say Infamous supply chain
attack on the SSH demon through a
package called
XZ this attack has been widely reported
in the media and I followed this to some
extent although I wouldn't call myself a
security researcher I didn't feel that
the media really dived very deeply in
depth into this and hopefully we will be
doing that today I want to start out
with we will cover what has already been
reported on us could you give a summary
of the attack and then we'll delve more
into details sure basically a malicious
actor created a command execution back
door in a popular Linux compression
Library lcma XC for short resulting in a
back door in another popular remote
access system which is open
SSH H this was an advanc software supply
chain attack with ausc hiding this
behavior from reviewers it was detected
on March 28 this year just one month
after it was injected and it was quickly
so it it did not enter stable
distributions which fortunately was a a
lucky thing because the the imagine if
you have a a back door open in more than
20 million potential open S servers
hanging on the internet you have a big
problem what would the attacker have
been able to do if this attack had been
distributed as I mentioned there was
something like more than 20 million op
SSH servers hanging on the internet that
means that a bad actor has access to
arit commands of the selected targets he
could wak havoc in a lot of places the
problem was contained but it could be
much worse than it was at the end this
is the ending of the thing but uh the
problem is that it open a lot of can of
worms what happen if this is not the
unique back door popular system in
hanging on the internet this is the
which we are taking into account right
now now have raise the point that there
could be other similar attacks that have
not been
detected I do want to come back to that
question but before we go there I'd like
you to describe how the attack was
detected pow developer named Andres
FR who detected a b performance issue
with the SSH server he was testing he
detected that the loging took half a
second more than usual so he decided to
investigate or to perform some internal
research on that first he extracted from
the tble from the distribution turble
for the open SSH he tried to look
something there but he found nothing
nothing relevant he then performed some
performance testing with the op SSH
service and he found that there was a
library which was a lcma library which
was acting as a as a CPU hog and he made
some debagging and he detected that that
library was doing something strange
which was modifying the system Library
modifying the table for functions and
injecting a different function which was
the pre-authentication function that SSH
uses for validation of the public key
presented by the client he decided to
look more in in depth in the lmca Taro
and he found that there was something
strange with the build script that
extracted from the testing files which
was highly ausc and was included in the
in the build system in the final binary
for the lcma library that mean that
probably that was a some strange thing
malware he did not perform reverse
engineering he asked for help for others
they found that there was something that
tried to open a system call for running
the uh commands passed by by the
attacker in the payLo in the
communication payLo so this this was
clearly a a back door not not for
authentication with SSH but for remote
codee ex execution
allowing the the attacker to run
arbitrary commands using the the
commands they decide on the vulnerable
system and it was also an an attack that
it was not repayable and it was gated
that means that only the owner of the
private key the right private key could
make the back door run otherwise the
system worked as as normal it dumped to
the normal crypto Exchange so it was a a
passive back door and this made
impossible for normal detection tools
unless the the back door is really
executed no tool could detect that it it
was there was a something strange on on
that but it was amazing how by by
accident by a a performance problem this
could be detected by a person which he
declared he was not a security analyst
so I think we were lucky on this I need
to discuss also in a bit later in the
interview the element of luck that was
involved and is that a good way to
detect things before we get to that you
raised a couple of points that I want to
come back to in my reading about this
and I only know a little bit about C and
I'm not involved with these security
issues at all but what struck me as hard
to understand is SS H is the application
it uses libraries which is how every
program works compression is a library
that it calls upon to do some step in
its process so my question was how could
a library that you call insert a back
door that affects the behavior at a much
higher level of the stack I think where
you begin to answer that is there is a
table that points to functions somewhere
in the process and that there isn't any
restriction that prevents a library from
going and changing how this table works
now did I understand that correctly and
can you say more about that that's a
very good question and complex to
explain okay op SSH does not link with
this library with a li lcma Library it
uses a a Sal or GP Library
but it's optional is not even linked
with many many op SSH distributions so
in fact this is an option that is
normally not enabled and never works in
normal open SSH installations but in
some Dr patches were added which enable
sshd to inform the uh the system the
service manager in many Linux systems
which is systemd when it has finished
starting
okay systemd is a common l in system and
Le systemd uses the XC Library okay so
the malicious leave the malicious leave
lcma Library installs an audit hook into
the dynamic Linker waiting for a
function name I have a a small check
here is RSA public decrypt this is the
name of the of the function that is used
by SSH
to perform the initial
authentication logic so the malware
through the uh system the dependency
managed to change dynamically the link
to this function so it worked with the
back door instead of running through the
normal the normal function it run
through the back door the back door
check simply key used to authenticate
is the the right one from the attacker
and then diverts the payload to the
system call which runs an a r command in
the in the system sshd the the server
the open SSH server normally runs with a
high privileges typically as root so if
you can execute the command as root you
are you are a king so this is the reason
why they they looked for open SSH
instead of running the in the in the
user space in the compressed library and
it was a very very interesting way of
without having a direct link from SSH to
the library you can in the library you
can manage to affect the third party uh
service up upwards so this is the the
key of the of the attack when I have
read about this it reminded me of there
are other attacks on the process runtime
and there have been efforts over time to
restrict things I don't recall the name
of this but there was an attack where a
function would be written into a area of
Heap and something like what we've been
talking about was used to get the
execution to point into that function so
there were changes made in the runtime
layout where certain areas were data
only and you simply could not execute
those areas the process would fail in
some other run times like Java you can
have quite a high degree of security
over what pieces of code have access to
what parts of the
runtime now I don't know uh equivalent
amount about C and we'll talk more about
remediation later but so we're right on
this I want to ask is there been any
discussion or is this fixable in such a
ways to say we can't allow a library to
have access to those functions pointers
or is that just how this runtime works
and it's not fixable absolutely it's
fixable the problem is that the
attackers made some changes that allow
for the library to be able to perform
this change of the the symbol table
allowing to inject the back door in the
in the up sshd diamond and uh this was
fixed but the idea was to add some kind
of performance uh improvements allowing
to change functions using um indirect
functions or I fun for shirt and this
this was added before the actual malware
were injected by The Bad actors they
have a plan they decided to First allow
in the library to perform this Dynamic
change of the functions in the Via
systemd and after that they inserted
when they were were aware that nobody
was looking they inserted the actual
malw I see that means they first
disabled uh security feature that would
have prevented the attack for
completely different reasons so they
said but their true reason was to
prepare the groundwork for step two
which was the attack very clever I think
now since we're talking about this might
be a good time to talk more about the
attacker which is some kind of entity
and is still mysterious what is known
about the
attacker one thing is to have evidence
of who could be after your attack and
other is attribution attribution is
quite difficult now but the good thing
here is that all the changes were done
on a public repository which is a jeub
version which has also a copy in the in
the jit uh Linux system for git a mirror
and we can see exactly which actions
were done by the Bad actors after a fact
obviously so there were two commed
authors mainly one named gatan gatan is
a common Chinese name but forget about
thinking that gatan is Chinese probably
and there was also one Hans Janssen
these two guys they are actually
personas they are actually fake
accounts were working coordinately to
perform some activity first gatan this
is a social social engineering attack
mainly because this gatan made a neutral
or innocuous commits for more than two
years since November
2021 he gained Confidence from the
maintainer the innocent person here the
L calling so he was promoted as
maintainer during June September
2022 another committer this Hans Jansen
then made two key commits not malicious
per se but preparing the field as you
mentioned for with this iPhone support
which open the the key for for the
attack there was also another fake
identities sock puppets like some one
named jigar Comer Dennis s they were
using in um ephemeral email systems they
they just made some some and send some
emails to the maintainer to the project
maintainer and to the um distribution
mailing lists asking for Readiness or
pushing for the malicious uh tals to be
included in the distributions these
pressure emails were done by different
person from the ones who were performing
the commits in the real Repository those
identities are really fake using
disposable addresses I mentioned for
social
engineering and um no red flag was was
open by by the actions by The Bad actors
because they worked very canonly with
without trying to make too much noise
committers were were even thanked by the
poor maintainer for their commits in
retrospect some dist maintainers show
concern on the pressure emails received
by these fake accounts for including the
versions in the stable release probably
the best mechanism for avoiding a worst
problem was the slowly Pace in which
Linux distributions work first when a
new change is done it enters the
unstable or experimental distributions
and only after a thir review it passes
to the stable to the stable ones so
obviously you you can have a install an
unstable version I have
myself in fact in my because I need to
be on the on the age of the last
versions but one thing is to have a a
malware in a normal distribution in
unstable distribution and a different
thing a de thing is to have the malware
in in a stable distribution which is
much worse so no red flags happened and
these two guys gatan and Hans Johnson
made the the decisive changes and game
there was three stages in the attack
first the neutral stage where gatan made
some contributions to the project and
gain confidence from the main maintainer
they asked the maintainer to be
maintainers back backa backa maintainers
which is normal thing when when you have
done a good work on a on a project you
can offer yourself as as a new
maintainer they deceive the original
maintainer and he approved some some
accesses for gatan
particularly so he he made and sign the
releases which were taken by the lenus
distributions for adding the the library
to the to their that distributions so
one month before the the day the the
attack was was found he made the the the
final the final step which was the
attack he added the the he changed in
the tarble not not in the source
repository but in the tarble he made a
small change in the build file in one of
the build files and with that change he
make the when when the project was
compiled from the sources the uh final
binary included the back door this was
the last the last step the attack step
okay all all they have to do is just
wait for different distributions to to
get the that enter to to get the
distribution installed on the end points
and then he they could choose which end
points to attack because they have the
the private key needed to perform the
back door to run the the back door
talking about the attacker was there any
additional forensic work done trying to
locate who the attacker might be based
on any information contained in the
commit yeah
after the fact is quite easy to see
exactly which were the the commits there
are many commits but most of them in the
first stage were neutral only the
commits I mentioned the change by that
Johson of the enabling the Eun
capability and the final final attacks
from Jatan where he uploaded the the new
releases the new malicious releases were
the key key point
later there were some some backs when
they using a tool called B Green because
of the of the the way the the back door
was injected there was a that some tools
were bending the the the process so they
they managed to fix some of the of the
bus after the after the malw was
distributed in some unstable Linux
distributions they were checked because
there there are number but not a big
number of malicious commits and after
the fact it was found exactly what which
were the the um things that there were
clearly trying to maybe avoid the
detection fixing fixing bus to avoid
detection or performing additional
prepation steps for the attack things
like time zone IP addresses were there
any clues even indicating where this
attacker might have been
located we have evidence but uh no
unquestionable attribution first that
gatan used a VPN for access all the time
he use a
Singaporean uh IP address address does
not mean that he is in Singapore of
course regarding the time zone used in
the commits and the work patterns we
have some some ideas they used UTC 8
plus 8 which is the Chinese time zone
obviously he his name is chin Chinese so
he tried to deade but in fact in some
commits probably he forgot to to change
the uh time zone and he was using UTC
plus two or plus three which is due to
the uh summertime change corresponds to
Eastern Europe and Israel also it
doesn't mean that the the the guy these
guys are on Europe or Eastern Europe
Israel but it's a it's a nice
interesting
in evidence okay and H obviously the
working the working pattern they work
from 9:00 a.m. to 6:00 p.m. in that in
that UTC plus two time time zone which
uh
resembles normal
normal working hours not nightly working
so uh all of these they didn't work on
holidays hackers the bad guys the
financial motivated bad guys normally
work on holidays
work whenever they want and they they
use a irregular pattern they are not
using the the working hours pattern
commits were done on the on the Chinese
holidays which which H for me is a clear
sign of this is not this guy is not
Chinese okay but not on Christmas and
and Christianity New Year so all this
evidence accumulates to think that we
are probably thinking about uh and a bad
actor not a not a financial motivated
actor but probably a state backed actor
which was operating on the on this time
so I don't know the latitude I know the
longitude not the latitude but
probably Eastern Europe is a is a clear
candidate and the most robust evidence
comes from the techniques and the P the
ATT pattern itself patience planning two
years more than two years planning this
is not a financial motivated B actor
which quickly runs for for more money
this this is probably the um other kind
of actors and I I think about APS or
state back Bad actors the target is also
not financially motivated actors they
are they are trying to get obviously
they can use a back door in SSH but
probably this is more for for spyware
for for acting information sensitive
information from certain systems so I
think that this makes the the all the
evidence accumulates on on the AP uh
candidate okay the ability to access SSH
would be only a step towards some other
type of attack so where do you see them
going with this if they were able to get
it in place probably I think they are
trying to use a surgical
surgical back door is not um fishing
attack they injected I mentioned 23
million op SSH potential installations
not all were were affected because there
was a there was a need of different
environmental conditions were need to
meet for the attacker to be able to to
be executed but they have a lot of
servers where they they could um use the
back door and I think that probably the
surgical attack to selected targets
would be the uh the reason behind the
the attack which ones I don't know
mainly M Microsoft who
knows now SSH logs whenever somebody
authenticates many security systems
would monitor these logs looking for
unusual authentications if it had gone
into the wild could it have been
detected through log
analysis through logs no way because uh
the back door was not doing anything in
the in the authentication phase it was
simply diverting the authentication and
it was running the back door which means
you will not find any uh failure
authentication in the locks you
understand yes got it okay no trace on
the locks so no no wave it could
detected but but using a different
different approach now we've been
talking a bit about how it was detected
how it could have been detected has
there been any discussion in the
community about is there a better way
for the community to distinguish between
real people and fake entities that are
cutouts you hit the nail this is the the
common problem with open source in open
source you can even uh be a totally
Anonymous if you make a good
contributions to the open source project
you are welcome and there is no betting
there is no um at least in the in
general you can perform your your
activity from bpn hiding your identity
totally using the names and you are
welcome this is a problem with open
source obviously and in the private
sector is this is not reasonable but in
in open source that was the way of
working to now and change this is almost
impossible so per maybe we have to to
for example the problem here was a small
change in the build in the TBO which was
released for the distributions to to
perform the compiling in in the this so
maybe this is the point where it could
be detected but this is also very
difficult because as you know the Taro
has the all source code but the um
compilation is quite complex quite
difficult and it's difficult to have a
automated system to understand if there
is a difference between the expected
output of the compilation and the the
real one the first C compiler canet made
some some hints and on this and how can
I trust the C compiler how how can I
trust the tools that make other tools
this is a a complex problem and is an
unsolved problem for now of course you
can have two different compilations one
with with one system and one with other
and you can compare if the results are
the same which is in this dual
compilation with different different
build systems probably you can you can
catch a difference in between the two
because for this back door to be enabled
you need a a particular environment in
the build the problem is that
compilation is is not uh repeatable and
uh
you can compile even even with the same
environment the same source code and get
different non-binary compliant output so
it's is quite difficult to do this this
is for example for the solar winds
system they try to change this and do a
one hermetic build and one non hermetic
build and compare the two outputs to
check if there are any difference so if
if someone can change source code in in
the in the build process that could be
detected the problem is that is not easy
because of the repeatability problem me
what you're talking about now is a way
that it could have been detected we
talked a little earlier about a degree
of luck in that someone who's not a
security specialist was doggedly
determined to get to the bottom of this
performance issue and he knew enough to
call in other experts when he saw
something that shouldn't be there you
also mentioned that my idea of checking
logs is not work what are some other
ways this might have been detected or in
a more General
principle how could this type of thing
be
detected first of all after the fact
detection is is easy I believe there are
now J rules for command line tools and a
lot of a lot of to for detecting for
example there are some program
capabilities analyzers there is one from
chenar name being C there is also a tool
named binarily which provide detection
rules for this particular malware the
problem is that they cannot detect it
before they are instructed to do so they
cannot detect
preventively there are also different
kind of tools which are runtime
monitoring tools
which Baseline the behavior of the
programs and libraries and report on
deviations from the normal behavior they
learned this might detect exploitation
right after it runs the problem with
this back door is that unless there is a
real backd door attack you don't see any
change in the normal behavior of the of
this sshd Dion so this makes even for
these tools quite difficult to to in
fact there was no known uh evidence of a
real Attack using this back door because
it was removed quite promptly from the
releases but even if this exploitation
happens these tools may detect them
because they they will see a system
called which was not before in the
normal learn behavior and they can
report this as a unusual unusual
activity so the problem with this is
that you have to instrument the end
systems you don't the the problem in the
in the at the source you detect them at
the end systems you can detect it at the
end systems obviously if the end systems
report them to the thread modeling tool
which gathers information from multiple
sites they could detect this is what
happens for example with tools like ones
from C strikes another another tool
vendors and uh they could detect that
there is an ongoing attack using this
sshd but this this is after the uh
malware enters the victims the end
victims okay so this is not also the
perfect thing to for detection obviously
detecting this the uh bad commits in the
source would be the best but is quite
difficult because you trust the the
contributors if they are fine and it's
quite difficult if they they use their
magic they can hide for example in this
case the back door was inserted in a
test file file in a test compressed file
because this is a compression Library so
the biner containing the actual malware
the actual back door was in a test file
and nobody opens a compressed test file
to check if there's something strange
there quite difficult to detect you're
not giving me a lot of confidence that
it would have been rapidly detected that
raises a question that you raised
earlier and I promise to come back to
this
people must now be asking how many more
similar not necessarily attacks on SSH
but equally severe attacks that we don't
know about because we didn't have some
good luck of a person noticing an
anomaly and then unraveling the code
changes which led to that there are more
out there now this is for sure which
projects I don't know there are some
projects under review for example all
the projects that are using IUN are been
under under review because this was the
the vector the the actors used for this
for this attack but obviously they can
use another techniques which are not
known for now and obviously it's quite
difficult to to prevent a malicious
activity when it's done by actors that
take the patients in the planification
for the attack so I I have no asked your
question I don't know in fact I don't
know if there are more gatans out there
working making their their magic on on
on other popular point this next
question we may have covered to some
extent but anything about lessons
learned that we have not yet covered
well we talk about how hard is to
prevent this intentional back doors
because they are done with by knowledge
people not script kitties which work was
known in as script Kies in when I was
young some authors pointed at system D
you know the systemd is the is the
bridge between the uh two libraries the
SSH Library the SSH executable and the
uh compression library that was attacked
this uh popular service manager opens a
large attack surface at third party
services for back door this is what bad
actor abused and system D have has many
eyeballs on it but is an an oscure
Library up the chain can poison all the
water than Downstream this was a a wake
up called for other projects that
depends on systemd to check exactly
which kind of back doors could be
inserted using this bridge Library the
systemd for example immediately after
after the attack was uncovered there was
a full request on the on the XC Library
for removing the IUN support and this
was was also a change in systemd to to
avoid using libraries for example the
the problem is that systemd uses XC
library and is not related to the attack
but what is the reason for systemd to
use this library is a nonsense so they
are skimmer eliminating all the spous
dependencies to keep a clean the main an
important element like like systemd this
is another learn lesson okay and
probably the the root cause uh with open
source security issues is probably the
the excess TR test I mention that this
is the way open source projects was uh
evolved in the past but this is is
getting a deep review now because
obviously important projects need much
more control on which person makes which
changes and this is probably will will
change a bit how open source projects in
the Linux ecosystem and other ecosystems
are done in the open source uh Community
the problem is how maintainers get
remunerated by their hard work if they
are working as volunteers there are some
ideas on how to finance by the uh
private sector by the government the
open source effort
and I think this could be another
another good thing and use also a
different approach I mentioned that
probably the attack could be detected if
if there was a mechanism to detect
problems in the build that lead to a
different binary from the one produced
by the pure sources you mentioned that
the exploit was in a test file that was
included in the final distribution
artifact that also sounds odd to me if
I'm running a Linux system and I want to
run sshd I should not need any of the
test files in my
distribution first am I correct about
this and is that another Avenue of
improvement no no the problem is that in
the table you have the source code in
the test files because when you run you
run also the test when you make the
build you run the test to check the de
the system build is correct correct so
obviously the the test files need to be
there in the source toal which is
compiled by the
distributions it's difficult if you
cannot get rid of the the test files and
obviously if if the test files I remove
probably the bad guys will find another
another place to to put their the the
malware so it's not it's not the I think
it's not the we're getting close to end
of time something I'd like your opinion
on is had this exploit been released in
the wild how would you rank it compared
to some of the more wellknown open
source attacks that have occurred in the
last few years well I think it's uh five
not 10 the uh CVSs score when the CV was
opened by Red Hat it was given a 10 10
is uh
apocalyptic in the past there was some T
also for example like welln L log
forj issu
received a 10 and but the problem there
is is that it was completely open and
there was a lot of every single 2.x
version of Love 4J was vulnerable so the
problem was
huge here the problem was uh much more
contained because it affected only a few
distributions not all the distributions
for example open suus deian deian
unstable arelin
and Fedora Fedora from Red Hat not the
small distributions also Kali Linux K
Linux which is used by by pent testers
is a the distribution of choice for pent
testers was affected interesting and uh
but for example lean stable or wtu or
many other distributions commercial ones
and so on were not affect so I I give
five the attack is serious because if it
could uh really get open access the
problem is that as this is um a back
door that makes no noise it could uh
left the time between the uh the
introduction and the detection good
range in the in the
Years perhaps the risk was high was
enormous but it was contained quickly so
for me it's a five not not a 10 thanks
God and thanks thanks to Andrew Andrew
freuden we owe freeer for for him for
for years as we come to a close were
there any aspects of this issue that we
have not covered that you'd like to
highlight I think we covered a lot of a
lot of things from the detection from
the uh how the uh the attackers work
they use a social engineering attack
this is this is the the key idea because
introducing the malware they need rights
to perform changes and to release the
distributions so social engineering is
the is the big the big deal for many
many attacks in the supply chain part of
the equation so I think this is
interesting to understand how the
attackers work how they uh gain
confidence how they exploit the
different the combination of techniques
they they they used is interesting
because with this information we can
prevent in the future similar attacks I
think this is the main benefit for this
knowledge for this attack I did forget
to mention that much of this
conversation was based on an article
that you wrote on the zyen blog on the
issue that will be linked in the show
notes is there anywhere else you'd like
people to find you on the internet well
I have a LinkedIn account if you want
you can reach me by email my email is
luis. Rodriguez at
y. it's been a pleasure speaking with
you thank you very much for speaking to
software engineering radio thank you
very much Robert the pleasure was mine
for software engineering radio this has
Ben Robert blumen thank you for
listening thanks for listening to SC
radio an educational program brought to
you by It software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at se-
radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our slack Channel at seo.
slack.com you can also email us at team
e-r. this and all other episodes of SC
radio is licensed under Creative Commons
license
2.5 thanks for listening